<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Abernethy 1</title>
             <editor role="editor" xml:id="NW"><persName>Nora White</persName>                  
                 <orgName>Maynooth University, Department of Early Irish</orgName></editor>
                <editor role="editor" xml:id="XS">
                    <persName>Xenia Spanachi</persName>
                    <orgName>University of Glasgow</orgName>
                </editor>
                <editor role="editor" xml:id="POC"><persName>Patricia O Connor</persName>
                <orgName>Maynooth University, Department of Early Irish</orgName></editor> 
                <funder>Irish Research Council (grant no. IRC/W001985/1) and Arts and Humanities Research Council (grant no. AH/W001985/1)</funder>
                <funder>
                <ref target="https://research.ie/funding/uk-ireland-collaboration-in-the-digital-humanities-research-grants%e2%80%af/?f=principal-investigator-led">UK-Ireland Collaboration in the Digital Humanities Research Grant</ref>
                </funder>
                <respStmt>
                <name ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7957-651X">Nora White</name>
                <resp>data collection, editing and encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
                 <respStmt>
                    <name xml:id="JB">Jef Bucas</name>
                      <orgName>Dublin Institute for Advanced Studies</orgName>
                    <resp>batch conversion to EpiDoc</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Xenia Spanachi</name>
                    <resp>encoding and editing</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <name></name>
                     <orgName></orgName>
                <resp><!--3d recording, technique and software used, date e.g. <date when="2003-09-17"/>--></resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                <name ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5880-4704">Patricia O Connor</name>
                <resp>editing and encoding</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>OG(H)AM</authority>
                <idno type="filename">S-PER-001</idno>
                 <idno type="CIIC"/>
                <idno type="CISP">ABNTY/1</idno>
                 <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</licence>   
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                         <country>Scotland</country>
                        <repository>National Museums Scotland</repository>
                        <idno type="invNo">IB98</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno type="geo">55.946991, -3.1891831</idno>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <msContents>
                          <msItem>                            
                            <textLang mainLang="xpi-Ogam">Potentially Pictish written in ogham script</textLang> <!--not sure on language its speculative-->                              
                           </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support><p><ref target="https://canmore.org.uk/site/27926/abernethy-churchyard-ogam-stone">Canmore</ref> <idno type="Canmore">27926</idno></p>
                                    <material type="stone">Sandstone</material> 
                                    <objectType key="monument">Cross-slab</objectType>                                   
                                    <dimensions unit="mm">                                         
                                            <height>360</height>
                                            <width min="200" max="230">200-230</width>
                                            <depth>70</depth>
                                     </dimensions>  
                                    <desc type="decoration">The upper section of the fragment features the remains of a common Pictish sculpture motif, the <rs type="decoration" key="PictishSymbol">high-stepping horse(s)</rs> (Forsyth 1996, 5). </desc>
                                </support>
                                <condition>This ogham-inscribed fragment of old red sandstone has been severely cut down and potentially represents only a small portion of the original cross slab and inscription. There are no signs which might indicate the original proportions of either. Three complete letters of the original inscription survive on the fragment, the ogham letters are very clear and well-preserved (ibid. 4). The upper half of the fragment is especially damaged, obscuring the area containing the carving of a horse or deer of which only two legs, facing left, now survive. Similarly, a semi-circular portion of the bottom left corner of the fragment <q>has been deliberately defaced</q> (Forsyth 1996, 5). 
                                </condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout style="other" rend="stemline">The ogham text is positioned below the symbol carving on a raised band which is <dim type="breadth" unit="mm">90mm</dim> broad and occupies the full width of the fragment (ibid. 5). The stem-line is <dim type="length" unit="mm">225mm</dim> in length and extends beyond the strokes of the outermost letters, indicating that the inscription <q>extended further in both directions</q> (ibid. 7). Forsyth theorises that <q>if the Abernethy fragment was part of the upper face of a recumbent</q> then an ogham inscription would have began in the bottom left-hand corner, rose vertically upwards and have continued across the top, down the right-hand side and conclude along the bottom with the portion under the horses hooves reading forward right-to-left (ibid. 7). 
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote>The individual strokes are deep U-section grooves that have been initially <rs type="execution"  key="pocked" ref="https://www.eagle-network.eu/voc/writing/lod/11.html">pocked and rubbed</rs>. The vowel strokes are straight and occupy the full ogham band. The component strokes are equally and generously spaced. The spacing of the extant letters is irregular and uneven although, as Forsyth cautions, it would be unwise to make an assesment on the spacing of the entire inscription on this basis as there is insufficient evidence surviving from the fragment. The first letter is comprised of five short oblique strokes to the left of the stem, with the individual strokes ranging from <dim type="length" unit="mm">35-40mm</dim> in length, and even spacing between strokes of <width unit="mm">65mm</width> in width. The second letter is one long stroke across the stem, <dim type="length" unit="mm">50mm</dim> in length, sloping forwards. The third letter consists of five long strokes, bound and perpendicular across the stem. The individual strokes measure <dim type="length" unit="mm">52mm</dim> in length, with even spacing amounting to a total width of <width unit="mm">55mm</width>. 
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace><placeName type="parish">Abernethy</placeName>, <placeName type="county">Perthshire</placeName>, <placeName type="country">Scotland</placeName>
                                <geo>56.333056, -3.311667</geo>
                            <note>National Grid Reference: NO 1900 1641</note></origPlace>
                            <origDate/><!--usually not known-->
                        </origin>
                        <provenance type="found" when="1890">Found in a churchyard in <date>1890</date> and presented to the National Antiquities Museum in <date>1892</date> by Alexander Laing.</provenance>
                        <provenance type="observed" when="2022-06-15">The fragment was observed and recorded by the OG(H)AM team on the <date>15th of June 2022</date> at <placeName><ref target="https://www.nms.ac.uk/search-our-collections/collection-search-results?entry=167115W">National Museums Scotland</ref></placeName>. </provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
             <encodingDesc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"><xi:include href="../charDecl.xml" parse="xml" xpointer="symbols"/></encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <calendarDesc>
                <calendar xml:id="julian">
                    <p>Julian Calendar</p>
                </calendar>
            </calendarDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="pgl">Primitive Irish</language>
                <language ident="sga">Old Irish</language>
                <language ident="mga">Middle Irish</language>
                <language ident="ga">Irish</language>
                <language ident="xpi">Pictish</language>   
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>     
                <keywords scheme="https://ontology.inscriptiones.org/type_of_inscription/#vocabularies">
                    <term ref="https://ontology.inscriptiones.org/type_of_inscription/#Commemorative">Commemorative</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <!-- <creation>Transcription from previous editor</creation> if not read by OG(H)AM team-->
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="draft">
            <listChange>
                <change when="2022-09-28" who="#JB">Jef Bucas autogenerated EpiDoc output from spreadsheet</change>   
                <change when="2024-01-22" who="NW">Nora White updated template, including removing # from bibl tag</change>
                <change when="2024-06-19" who="#NW">Updated template for Scottish oghams autogeneration from spreadsheet</change>
                <change when="2024-07-11" who="#XS">Xenia Spanachi added and encoded further data, including information on publication content, layout, execution, provenance and condition</change>
                <change when="2024-07-25" who="#POC">Added encodingDesc for character encoding.</change>
                <change when="2024-09-10" who="#POC">Added paragraph to support and NGR details to origPlace, closed unused elements, commented out apparatus and translation</change>
                <change when="2025-02-26" who="#POC">Proofreading updates and added information from Forsyth 1996.</change>
                <change when="2025-03-12" who="#POC">Moved information from apparatus to layout, and moved information from commentary to apparatus, added attributes to material and object type.</change>
                <change when="2025-03-13" who="#POC">Moved information from layout to handNote, deleted enter key whitespaces to fix stemline, added bound I character to the edition</change>
                <change when="2025-03-14" who="#POC">Added bound Q character to the edition, added decoration description encoding to support, updated layout to remove ellipsis</change>
                <change when="2025-03-18" who="#POC">Updated condition to replace symbol term with motif, deleted xml:lang attribute from translation element, added hyphen back to cross-slab, updated measurements from m to mm.</change>
                <change when="2025-03-26" who="#POC">Update object type key attribute value to monument for filtering</change>
                <change when="2025-03-27" who="#POC">Added country to origPlace and secondary location coords</change>
                <change when="2025-04-17" who="#NW">Removed hi (previously needed for babel font) from edition. Added layout style and rend.</change>
                <change when="2025-05-02" who="#POC">Added NMS image and copyright, added reading to apparatus, updated execution, added lang code to persName in commentary</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="SCO/S-PER-001-Abernethy1.png"><desc>Image of Abernethy ogham inscription. Copyright: <ref target="https://www.nms.ac.uk/search-our-collections/collection-search-results?entry=167115">National Museums Scotland</ref></desc></graphic>
        <media url="Complete" mimeType="text/html"><desc><!--3d model by Megan/Gary/? on SketchFab/3dhop--></desc></media>
    </facsimile>    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" subtype="ogham" xml:space="preserve" xml:lang="xpi-Ogam" resp="#XS"><!--Language unsure-->              
                <ab>
                    <lb n="1" style="text-direction:left"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/><g ref="#bound_Q"/>ᚋ<g ref="#bound_I"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/> 
                </ab> 
            </div>
            <div type="edition" subtype="transliteration" xml:lang="xpi-Ogam" xml:space="preserve" resp="#KF">
                <ab>
                     <lb n="1" style="text-direction:left"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/><g ref="#bound_Q"/>M<g ref="#bound_I"/><gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/> 
                </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="apparatus">
                <listApp>
                    <app n="1">
                        <note>There is some debate regarding the direction in which the ogham text should be read due to the conflicting orientations of the text and the horses. Forsyth is in favor of reading the ogham script right-to-left as based on the form of the recumbent Meigle 11 (1996, 6). This allows <q>both horse and ogham to go forward in opposite directions simultaneously</q> (ibid. 6). Moreover this arrangment of the text facing in, is in alignment with other seventh century Scottish gravestones. Rhys, Allen and Macalister favoured the interpretation that the <q>horses are walking in procession along the ogham band</q> and read:  </note>
                        <rdg source="FOR1996">IMN</rdg>
                    </app>
                    <app n="2">
                        <note>Due to the limited evidence from the surviving letters there is little that can be discerned from the Abernethy ogham fragment other than that it preserves valuable evidence for the use of <q>bind-strokes outside the Northern Isles</q>. The only other example is found nearby at Inchyra (ibid. 8).</note>
                    </app>
                </listApp>
            </div>
            <div type="translation">
                <p>The extant portion of the inscription is insufficient for producing a translation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
                         <p>Unfortunately, the ogham fragment is too short to yield any meaningful linguistic analysis. However, Forsyth highlights that the presence of the letter Q may suggest a variant of the formula word MAQQI. In this context, the letters MI, which follow the letter Q, could signify <q>a handful of Irish male and female personal names [that] begin Mi-</q> such as <persName xml:lang="sga">Minchloth</persName> or <persName xml:lang="sga">Midgna</persName> (1996, 9).</p>
                         <p>Despite the fragmentary state of this text, Forsyth notes that <q>it provides important evidence for the use of ogham at a major ecclesiastical site</q> (1996, 9).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography">
                 <listBibl>
                     <bibl><ptr target="FOR1996"/>
                     <citedRange>2-10</citedRange>
                     </bibl>
                 </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>


